Alright, בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. It’s ב באלול Bet B'Elul and we
are on סנהדרין לט Sanhedrin Lamed Tet right at the top. We
finished yesterday talking about רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, who had
a number of משלות, meshalot, a number of parables regarding foxes. In
fact, the גמרא Gemara tells us he had three hundred, we only
have three. As you can see this beautiful thing is coming up.
So we are going to read the three parables and take a
few minutes going through רש״י Rashi and looking at this parable. It’s
very famous, very beautiful, cryptic in the גמרא, Gemara, so we’ll take
a couple of minutes with it and then move on. All right.
So we’re on top of לט, Lamed Tet, עמוד א. Amud Aleph.
The last line in לח ב Lamed Chet Bet said ואנו אין
לנו אלא שלש. V'anu ein lanu ela shalosh. So now we’re looking
at three parables, here they come. It will seem completely like, "Where
are we talking about?" But here they come. אבות יאכלו בסר ושני
בנים תקהינה. Avot yochlu boser v'shinei banim tikhena. The fathers are eating
a raw fruit and the sons, the teeth of the sons will
suffer, will be dull. That’s number one. Second one is מאזני צדק
אבני צדק, Moznei tzedek avnei tzedek, the scales of justice and the
stones because the stones were the weights. And the third one is
צדיק מצרה נחלץ ויבא רשע תחתיו, Tzadik mitzara nechelatz v'yavo rasha tachtav,
the righteous wiggles his way out of trouble and the evil one
gets in under him. All right? We’re going to look at רש״י
Rashi because right now it’s not obvious what’s the parable here, right?
So we’re going to take a minute and look at רש״י. Rashi.
All right. Top of לט. Lamed Tet. אבות יאכלו בסר. Avot yochlu
boser. Everybody got the דיבור? dibur? Okay. הוא שרימה השועל את הזאב,
Hu sherima hashu'al et haze'ev,
משל mashal הוא שרימה השועל את הזאב. hu sherima hashu'al et haze'ev.
The fox tricked the wolf ליכנס לחצר היהודים בערב שבת. leikanes l'chatzer
hayehudim b'erev Shabbat. The wolf and the fox are now in a
Jewish quarters on ערב שבת Erev Shabbat ולתקן עמהם צרכי סעודה ויאכל
עמהם בשבת. ul'takein imahem tzarchei seudah v'yochal imahem b'shabbat. So this is
the wolf, he’s coming into the Jewish quarter to have שבת Shabbat
meal.
וכשבא ליכנס חברו עליו במקלות. ukh'sheba leikanes chivru alav b'maklot. When he
came into enter, all the people came to beat him up. בא
להרוג את השועל. ba laharog et hashu'al. The שועל shual is with
him, he’s like, "Hey, why are they all," the wolf says, "why
are they all against me? Probably because of you." The שועל shual
says אמר amar לא הלקוך אלא בשביל אביך. lo hilkucha ela bishvil
avikha. We’re getting into the פסוקים, psukim, right? They don’t beat you
for yourself, for your own sins, but for the
father שפעם אחת התחיל לסייען בסעודה ואכל את כל נתח טוב. shepa'am
achat hitchil l'say'an b'seudah v'achal et kol netach tov. Your father came
here just the same like you’re coming and started eating with them
but he gobbled up the whole meal and didn't leave them anything.
אמר לו, amar lo, the wolf to the fox אמר לו amar
lo ובשביל אבא אני לוקה? uvishvil aba ani loke? For my father
I'm now getting beaten up? אמר לו, הן. amar lo, hen. Okay.
So because he’s quoting us the פסוק, pasuk, the fox האבות יאכלו
בסר. ha'avot yochlu boser. This is something that happens and it’s again
just like the אגדות Aggadot of yesterday deserves a much more good
conversation.
But if you have kids then or if you’re a kid to
somebody you can see that sometimes things that happen to our parents
follow us into our life. And then he’s upset about that. Now
the fox is going to trick the wolf. אבל בוא עמי ואראך
מקום לאכול ולשבוע. aval bo imi v'arekha makom le'echol v'lisbo'a. Come with
me says the fox to the wolf, I will show you a
place where you can eat and be satiated.
בא לו על הבאר. ba lo al habe'er. There you go. ועל
שפתו מוטל עץ v'al sefato mutal etz and וחבל מושכב עליו. v'hachevel
mushkav alav. So here is the piece of wood and there’s a
rope
and and and and and ובשני ראשי החבל שני דלאים קשורים. ubishnei
rashei hachevel shenei dlayim kshurim. Two buckets. נכנס השועל
בדלי העליון, nikhnas hashu'al badli ha'elyon,
right? We know this. The fox goes into the upper bucket והכביד.
v'hikhbid. So now there’s weight, right? וירד למטה ודלי תחתון עלה. v'yarad
l'mata udli tachton ala. So when this bucket goes
down this bucket the other bucket goes up. אמר לו הזאב amar
lo haze'ev למה אתה נכנס לשם? lama ata nikhnas l'sham? Why are
you going there? אמר לו amar lo יש כאן בשר וגבינה לאכול
ולשבוע yesh kan basar v'gvina le'echol v'lisbo'a
and והראה לו דמות הלבנה במים כדמות עיגול כמין גבינה. v'hera lo
dmut halevana bamayim kidmut igul k'min gvina. The moon and cheese is
really old. The moon being, right. The what? The moon being like
a cheese. Right, right, that's a Talmudic saying. Okay, so the fox
goes down
and like there's let's say there's some water, so there's a reflection
and the wolf stands up here and looks and he says wow
what's in there? So because of the reflection it looks same like
there's cheese and food to eat. Wow. אמר לו, Amar lo, אני
היאך ארד? ani heich ered? How will I go down? אמר לו,
Amar lo, הכנס אתה בדלי העליון, hikanes ata badli ha'elyon, right? So
now let's imagine there's one bucket down, one bucket up here. נכנס
והכביד וירד
ודלי שהשועל עליו עלה. nichnas vehichbid veyarad vedli shehashual alav ala. So
clearly when this bucket goes down, kind of like a seesaw, this
bucket will go back up.
אמר לו, Amar lo, היאך אני עולה? heich ani ole? So the
wolf now is down in the well, right? He says to the
fox, how am I going up? אמר לו, Amar lo, he quotes
him our פסוק pasuk from משלי, Mishlei, צדיק מצרה נחלץ ויבא רשע
תחתיו. tzadik mitzara nechelatz vayavo rasha tachtav. לאו כך כתיב? lav kach
ktiv?
Right? So the righteous gets out of trouble and the bad guy
goes under him. That's our פסוק pasuk in משלי. Mishlei. But now
it has a peculiar thing. Wouldn't it be the other way around?
Meaning that he was tricked and he was stuck on the bottom.
This one goes one, right? This one goes second.
First bucket goes down, second bucket goes stays up. First bucket goes
down with the שועל. shual.
The wolf says, how do I get in? Jump into this bucket.
As soon as he goes down, exactly, this bucket goes up. Now
he gets out. The שועל shual is considered the
smart, the and the זאב ze'ev is considered the one that's being
right that's gobbling up the food, that's being like not nice. This
is the our rabbis. But we still have a problem. This was
two parables if you noticed.
His fathers were mean, right? So now he gets punished. The righteous
goes up and the evil one goes under him. But we have
one more פסוק. pasuk. And this is what the שועל shual says
to the זאב ze'ev too. He says, right? צדיק מצרה נחלץ ויבא
רשע תחתיו. tzadik mitzara nechelatz vayavo rasha tachtav. לאו כך כתיב? lav
kach ktiv? מאזני צדק וכולי. moznei tzedek vechulei.
So this third פסוק pasuk is hard to understand. He had the
weight for a just man and the one he went down all
the way. Okay, so the מהרש״א, Maharsha, this is now a 15th,
16th century, he says the fox was smarter even than what seems.
When he went down in the because the fox. Wait why? One,
he weighs less. Two, the wolf could have looked down and be
like what am I going in there?
So how do you how do you like guarantee that while you
I don't know if that's the right way to teach kids, but
how do you guarantee that if you like in the trickery you
don't bind yourself, right? So the מהרש״א Maharsha says that the שועל
shual when he went down, he put two stones of equal weight,
more than him, less than the wolf, into the
bucket.
Okay. Add the stones, right? So there's stones here. Okay. They're more
than him, but less than the wolf.
That's the math, okay. So he put those stones in because he
says if the wolf doesn't come when he's down, he's going to
remove one stone. Now that stone, which is more than him, right,
is going to help him go back out. And if not, then
the wolf will help him come out.
Morning parable, clever, right? Alright. Now we're starting ממש mamash on ל״ט
lamed tet and we're going to have ten back and forth conversations
between a כופר, kofer, אפיקורוס, apikorus, and some say actually the emperor
or the Roman ruler, and different rabbis. Alright.
Plowing through. אמר לו כופר לרבן גמליאל, amar lo kofer leRabban Gamliel,
number one. אלהיכם גנב הוא, eloheichem ganav hu, your God is a
thief. דכתיב, dechtiv, ויפל ה׳ אלהים תרדמה על האדם ויישן. vayapel Hashem
Elokim tardema al ha'adam vayishan. And we know the rest of the
פסוק, pasuk, God caused man, human, Adam to sleep, and what did
he do while Adam was asleep? He took his rib, right, and
created the woman. So in essence he stole his rib. אמרה ליה
ברתיה, amra lei beratei, the daughter of the כופר, kofer, the daughter
possibly of the emperor, she said to רבן גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel, שבקיה
ואנא מהדרנא ליה. shavkeia ve'ana mehadrena lei. Let sit down, rabbi. Oh,
is it the daughter of רבן גמליאל? Rabban Gamliel? No, it's the
daughter of the
כופר. kofer. But as he created Adam, so it's really his possession,
do what he wants with... he's not really stealing from something that
wasn't his.
Right? Or if I give you money and then it's yours, I
can't just go and take it back whenever I want. No, that's
different. But what I'm saying is ה׳ Hashem is the creator of
everything, right? So in a sense he's the possessor of everything. So
he's not like stealing from somebody's, he created that rib as well
as the man. Right, but there is something to okay again, this
is along the crazy tensions of the אגדות Aggadot that we've been
dealing with yesterday and some of them we'll see today. Like there's
truth to it, but there's also another side, because let's say if
I have money and I'm going to give it to my kids,
can they come take it?
No,
I'm not... I'm not God, but that's not the same. I think
again, if we had time, these are all different levels or different
ways that various כופרים, kofrim, various אפיקורסים, apikorsim, not even אפיקורסים, apikorsim,
questioning can attack our text and our teaching. So this is just
one. Yeah. And Caesar's case or an emperor is... Yeah, yeah, yeah.
That's what I said, the emperor or the ruler. Okay. It's not
obvious from the Hebrew. כופר kofer is not קיסר, Keisar, but the
understanding of the commentators is that it is the emperor. Okay. The
daughter, the daughter of the emperor says to רבן גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel,
sit, I will answer him.
אמרה ליה: Amra leh: דוכוס אחד. duchus echad. Give me a judge.
אמר לה: Amar lah: למה לך? Lama lach? Why do you need
a judge? She tells him a horrible story that happened to her.
ליסטים באו עלינו הלילה ונטלו ממנו קיתון של כסף והניחו לנו קיתון
של זהב. Listim ba'u aleinu halailah venatlu mimenu kiton shel kesef vehinichu
lanu kiton shel zahav. I am stressed. I don't know what to
do. Robbers came last night. They took away
a bucket of gold and instead they left us a bucket of
gold. No, the other way around.
Took away a bucket of silver and left us a bucket of
gold. Thank you. אמר לה: Amar lah: והלוואי שיבוא עלינו בכל יום.
Ulevai sheyavo aleinu bechol yom. I wish these kind of robbers would
come every day. She says: ולא יפה היה לו לאדם הראשון שנטלו
ממנו צלע אחת ונתנו לו שפחה לשמשו? Velo yafeh hayah lo l'Adam
HaRishon she-natlu mimenu tzela achat venatnu lo shifcha leshamsho? Okay, so again,
I
in my dreams we will have a whole course about אגדות Aggadot
of סנהדרין Sanhedrin here. But without and
without getting bogged on שפחה shifcha and לשמשו, leshamsho, but basically Adam
got a good deal. He lost one rib, true, we feel for
him, but he got a he got an עזר כנגדו, ezer kenegdo,
he got a partner for life. אמר לה: Amar lah: now the
emperor is not like okay, he gets it. הכי קאמינא, Hachi kamina,
I understand. אבל לשקלה בהדיא. Aval lishkleh bahadya. He should have done
it openly, like he shouldn't have come to Adam when he's asleep.
אמר לה: Amar lah: אייתי לי אומצא דבישרא. Aitei li umtza devisra.
Bring me like a chunk of meat. אייתו לה. Aitu lah. וטבייתא
בחשא אפיקתא. Uteveita bachasha apikta. She started preparing it over the fire,
over the ashes and yeah, preparing it for a meal. אמרה ליה:
Amra leh: she says to her father, אכול מהאי. Echol mehai. Eat
this. אמר לה: Amar lah: מאיסא לי. Me'isa li. Well, this is
disgusting. I just watched how it came from the animal and all
that. אמר לה: Amar lah: לאדם הראשון נמי אי הוו שקלוה בהדיה
הוה מאיסא ליה. Le'Adam HaRishon nami ei havu shaklu bahadya havah me'isa
leh. Had he seen the whole process,
it would have been disgusting for him too. It was better in
hiding. Okay, number next one. אמר ליה כופר לרבן גמליאל. Amar leh
kofer le'Rabban Gamliel. Another incident. ידענא אלהיכו מאי קא עביד. Yadana Eloheichu
mai ka avid. I know what your God is doing. והיכן יתיב.
Veheichan yativ. And where He
sits. אתנגד ואתנח. Itneged ve'itnach. He's now like
restless and kind of feeling uncomfortable
and sighing. אתנח, itnach, like אתנחתא etnachtah in the trope.
Okay. רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel says: אמר ליה: Amar leh: מאי האי?
Mai hai? What's the matter? אמר ליה: Amar leh: בן אחד יש
לי בכרכי הים ויש לי געגועים עליו. Ben echad yesh li be-karkei
hayam veyesh li ga'agu'im alav. I have one son at the end
of the sea and I'm missing him. רבן
גמליאל Rabban Gamliel says: בעינא דמחווית ליה ניהלי. Ba'ina demachveit leh nihali.
He says, show him to me. Where is he? אמר ליה: Amar
leh: מי ידענא היכא ניהו? Mi yadana heicha nihu? How in the
world am I supposed to know where he is? He's somewhere in
the world. אמר ליה רבן גמליאל Amar leh Rabban Gamliel says to
the emperor: דאיכא בארעא לא ידעת דאיכא בשמיא ידעת? De'ika be'ara lo
yadatt de'ika bishmaya yadatt? You don't know what's going on on the
earth, you want to claim you know what's going on in the
heaven? Next. אמר ליה כופר לרבן גמליאל. Amar leh kofer le'Rabban Gamliel.
The emperor says to רבן גמליאל. Rabban Gamliel. כתיב מונה מספר לכוכבים
מאי
רבותיה? Ketiv moneh mispar lakochavim mai rabutei? It says about your God
that He can count the stars. What's the big deal? אנא מצנא
למימן כוכבי. Ana mtzana lemeiman kochvei. I can also count the stars.
Now, what is the problem? If somebody says to you now, I
can count the stars, you're like, okay, God forbid if you say
how much, they say there is 23 billion and whatever number I
will make up, you will have to say okay I guess, right?
Because what am I going to do now? Count and check you?
We don't know. So this is רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel has to
think of a different trick. אייתי חבושי. Aitei chavushi. He brings quinces,
a fruit. שדי בערבילא. Shadei be'arbila. He throws it in a mixer.
וכמהדר להו. Vechamadar lehu.
He starts he starts... Mixing it and twirling it to make it
into a jam. אמר ליה Amar lei, *Amar lei*, רבן גמליאל Rabban
Gamliel *Rabban Gamliel* to the כופר *kofair*, מנינהו מנינהו *minyaneihu minyaneihu*, like
count it. Here, count those fruits. אמר ליה amar leih. *Amar lei*,
אוקמהו *ukmeihu*, like stop mixing then I'll be able to count it.
אמר ליה Amar lei, *Amar lei*, רקיע נמי הכי הדרא *rakia nami
hachi hadra*, the sky's also turning around while you're counting, so if
you can't count the fruits in the thing in front of you...
And some say this parable went a little bit, or not parable,
this discussion went a little different. איכא דאמרי הכי *Ika d'amri hachi*,
אמר ליה *amar lei*, מני לי כוכביא *mani li kochvaya*, some say
that the כופר *kofair* said to רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel, *Rabban Gamliel*
count the stars. רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel *Rabban Gamliel* says אימא לי
כוכיך ושיניך כמה הוו *eima li kuchecha v'shinecha kama hava*, tell me
about your teeth and your molars, how many are there? שדא ידיה
לפומיה *Shada yadei l'pumei*, he reached his hand, the emperor, to his
mouth, וכמני להו *v'kamani lahu*, he started counting. אמר ליה *Amar lei*,
דאיכא בפומך לא ידעת דאיכא ברקיע ידעת *deika b'pumeich lo yad'at deika
b'rakia yad'at*, you don't even know what's going on inside your mouth
and you want to say you know what's going on in the
heavens?
Next. אמר ליה כופר לרבן גמליאל *Amar lei kofair l'Rabban Gamliel*,
yes, the emperor, the Epicurus says to רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel *Rabban
Gamliel*, מי שברא הרים לא ברא רוח *mi shebara harim lo bara
ruach*. Now we have the claim, and I think each one of
those is a reflection of a deeper misunderstanding of how we see
God, right? So the next one maybe more obvious, he says, the
one who created mountains did not create wind, because it says in
a פסוק pasuk *pasuk* in עמוס *Amos*, כי הנה יוצר הרים ובורא
רוח *ki hinei yotzer harim u'vorei ruach*, right? It says about God's
creation, uses two words, יוצר *yotzer* and בורא *vorei*. In English they're
both translated into create. In Hebrew they're a little bit different. The
understanding is, you produce? יצר *Yatzar* is to produce, it's also to
form. So one of the explanation is that לברוא *livro*, on the
other hand, לברוא *livro* is to do something out of nothing, which
is an ability a creation only God has. And people, even when
they're creative, they're called יצירתיים *yetziratiyim*, they're יוצרים *yotzrim*, but they're not
called בוראים *borim*. We don't have that ability. So it says this
about God: he creates mountains and he creates בורא רוח *borei ruach*.
אלא מעתה גבי אדם דכתיב Dechtiv, ויברא ויצר הכי נמי *Ela me'ata
gabi adam d'chtiv vayivra vayitzer hachi nami*. Okay, so also about man
it says, it talks about man in two different verbs: one is
לברוא *livro*, something out of nothing, and one is ליצור *litzor*. Like
maybe if we again at the risk of going to a place,
you know, to the edge of the universe kind of thing, but
if we remember the hours of creation from yesterday, what was created
in each hour, the בריאה *b'ria* is like the raw material and
then the יצירה *yetzira* is to fashion out of that raw material
the shape of the human, right? Could have been anything, but the
בריאה *b'ria* is to collect this out of nothing and make something.
Okay. Wait, sorry, what does it say by אדם *Adam*? That also
if we go to בראשית *Bereishit*, you know, it says ויברא ויצר
*vayivra vayitzer*. Both verbs. Yes, both for the אדם *Adam*. Create human.
Yes. I in an effort to understand him, I'm trying to look
at what we read yesterday and saying maybe inventing the material is
the בריאה *b'ria*, something out of nothing, and the יצירה *yetzira* is
to create the shape out of that material. Possibly. Again, possibly we're
talking about things we don't know. So the guy says: Yeah, exactly,
that's what I mean. מי שברא זה לא ברא זה *mi shebara
zeh lo bara zeh*. It's possible that there's two different creators in
the creation of man, and different creators created different parts. So
רבן גמליאל *Rabban Gamliel* is like kind of in what we would
say in our own times: Are you serious? טפח על טפח יש
בו באדם ושני נקבים יש בו מי שברא זה לא ברא זה
*tefach al tefach yesh bo b'adam u'shnei nekavim yesh bo mi shebara
zeh lo bara zeh*. Like man is made from different parts. Do
you mean to say? A טפח על טפח *tefach al tefach*. Like
like we're I guess different pieces, composite.
Okay. שנאמר shene'emar.
*she'ne'emar*, we bring a פסוק pasuk *pasuk* from תהילים *Tehillim* to prove
this, right? הנוטע אוזן הלא ישמע ואם יוצר עין הלא יביט *hanotea
ozen halo yishma v'im yotzer ayin halo yabit*. That's what you mean?
It's like somebody that plants an ear in the body and creates
the eye. That's what you mean, that there's two different people? אמר
ליה אין *Amar lei in*, yes. רבן גמליאל *Rabban Gamliel* asks him:
ובשעת מיתה כולן נתפייסו *u'bish'at mita kulan nitpaisu*? Okay, so if you
have different creators, now when it comes time for the human being
to pass from the world, what, they all make peace? with each
other and are like yes, this is the right time or each
one takes its part at a different time? Whoa, that's not a
very good response considering how aging works. But so you think that
if the... well why? I mean various faculties at different times during
your life, so I don't know. If I was the guy, yeah,
exactly, like but
still like once but you die all at once. You die all
at once. Yeah. Right, but I'm just saying for time and different
parts of you mean at different points then. Okay, so I tend
to think that each the reason this is here and we're looking
at it, each one of these claims probably has something to it.
And then the question is like what do we do with it?
Yes. And then back back to the music. Yes. This, I think
this last statement of Rabban Gamliel is pretty profound. We can't talk
about right now but the Greco-Roman god pantheon did not have all
powerful gods. They might have supernatural powers but they're not like our
God. Right. But the Christians who would have been starting up during
this Roman era had what looks to us like multiple all powerful
figures. Okay. And so Rabban Gamliel is arguing against both of them.
Right. Right. At the same time in one line. Right. Right. Right.
Yes. So again, okay. אמר לו Amar lo. ההוא אמגושא amgusha, לאמימר.
So אמגושא, Rashi says מכשף, mechashef, some say like a Persian priest.
מפלגך ולעילא דהורמיז מפלגך ולתתא דאהורמיז. Mi-palgech u-l'eila de-Hurmiz, mi-palgech u-l'tatta de-Ahurmiz.
Okay, so Hurmiz and Ahurmiz, two different gods. Zoroastrianism, right? Like Ormazd
or something like that. Yeah, yeah, yeah. Like Zoroastrianism. Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Okay, so two different gods. One is Ormazd. This is much, much
later too.
אמימר Amemar and it's Aramaic. So he says in your body is
created to different parts. From the waist up, it's one god and
from the waist down, it's another god. אמר לו. Amar lo,
אי הכי איך שבקיה אהורמיז להורמיז לעבורי מיא בארעיה. I hachi heichi
shabkeih Ahurmiz le-Hurmiz l'avorei maya be-araia. Like if so, right, this is
like two different pieces of two different gods. Picture it as two
different countries. So how does one let the other pass water, go
to the bathroom basically? Right. How this is like not a fair
division. One part gets all the intake and the other one has
the outtake. Not not possible. Okay, end of that argument. This cannot
happen because doesn't make sense. Next. אמר לו קיסר לרבן תנחום. Amar
lo Keisar le-Rabban Tanchum.
תא ליהוו כולן לעם חד. Ta lehevu kullan le-am chad. Let's all
be one people or kind of aren't we all one people? We
should all be one people. אמר ליה, sure. One tiny problem. אנן
דמהלינן לא מצנין מהוי כוותייכו. Anan de-mahalinan lo matzinan mihvei kevataichu. We
circumcise and you guys, we're not like you, you guys don't do
the same. אתו מהליתו והוו כוותן. Atu mahlitu ve-hevu kevatan. So it's
great that you all want us to be one people, but we
can't be like you, so why don't you all be like us?
אמר לו, שפיר קאמרת, shapir ka-amart, great idea. And also while we're
at it, מיהו כל דזכי למלכא דשדיוהו לביבר. Mihu kol de-zaki le-malka
dashdyuhu le-beivar.
Anyone that disagrees with the king, we're going to throw him to
the animals. So and thus he kills who lose, right? A little
bit, yes.
Okay. Goes into the, yes. שדיוהו לביבר ולא אכלוהו. Shadyuhu le-beivar ve-lo
achluhu. So they threw him, I guess Amemar, to the animal cage
and they didn't eat him. אמר לו ההוא מינא, Amar lo hahu
mina, the
another min that's listening. האי דלא אכלוהו משום דלא כפין. Hai de-lo
achluhu mishum de-la kafin. They're just not hungry right now, so that's
why they didn't eat him. Not because of something. Okay. שדיוהו לדידיה
ואכלוהו. Shadyuhu l'didia ve-achluhu. So they're like okay, you think they're not
hungry? Throw this guy into the cage and let's see what happens.
שדיוהו ואכלוהו. Shadyuhu ve-achluhu. It's the story of Abraham and his brother.
Yes, and it comes back in Daniel, right? And Daniel also, this
comes back. Right.
Again, I'm not sure what to make of all of this, but.
So this probably could have been a Christian. The מינא? mina? Could
be, because
that was the term used for Christians. The מין min or the...
could be. Okay. אמר לו כופר לרבן גמליאל. Amar lo kofer le-Rabban
Gamliel. Back. אמריתו כל בי עשרה שכינתא שריא. Amritu kol be-asara shechinta
sharya. You tell us that wherever there's a minyan, wherever there's ten
people together, the שכינה שורא, shechina shora, the Shekhinah dwells there. כמה
שכינתא איכא כריא. Kama shechinta ika karya. רגע רגע לא. Rega rega
lo. כמה שכינתא. Kama shechinta.
How many Shekhinah is there? If every ten... If every ten that
gather, if every מנין minyan that gather have their own שכינה, shchina,
how many שכינה shchina could there be? איכא קרא לשמיה מחוי באפתקא.
ika karya lishme machvei be-apatka.
He calls רבן גמליאל calls the servant of the emperor and he
slaps him on the back, shoulder, neck, whatever, he kind of slaps
him up. אמר ליה אמאי? amar leih amai? What, why are you
hitting the poor servant? He says על שימשא בביתא. al shimsha be-veita.
I'm upset that you let the sun into your house. שימשא בביתא
דקיסר. shimsha be-veita de-keisar.
The sun is in the house of the emperor. אמר ליה. What,
like you're crazy? שימשא אכולי עלמא ניחא. shimsha a-kulei alma nicha. The
sun is in the whole world. Of course רבן גמליאל, all these,
right, you lead them into something from which the conclusion's like, oh
yeah, I see you think this way so of course. ומה שימשא
דחד מן אלף אלפי ריבוא שימשי דקמי קודשא בריך הוא ניחא לכולי
עלמא לכולי עלמא שכינתא דקדוש ברוך הוא על אחת כמה וכמה. u-ma
shimsha de-chad min elef alfei ribo shimshai de-kamei kudsha brich hu nicha
le-kulei alma le-kulei alma shchinte de-kadosh baruch hu al achat kama ve-kama.
I’m not sure we can parse it maybe a little sharper,
but the point is if the sun, which is only one out
of the thousands of thousands of creations of הקדוש ברוך הוא, ha-kadosh
baruch hu, can shine everywhere equally, קל וחומר kal va-chomer על אחת
כמה וכמה, al achat kama ve-kama, all the more so the שכינה
shchina which can be in different places. There's some stuff that's kind
of interesting, says he's also showing,
רבן גמליאל is showing that the heretic is, he's showing that
רבן גמליאל is saying that even the sun, which is a physical
object, can shine in more than one place than הקדוש ברוך הוא,
ha-kadosh baruch hu, which is non-physical, or like הקדוש ברוך הוא's ha-kadosh
baruch hu presence even more so that can be anywhere. Okay,
next one also kind of a little complicated, I'm not clear what's
connected here together. אמר ליה ההוא מינא לרבי אבהו. amar leih hahu
mina le-rabbi abbahu. Okay, another challenge. אלהיכם גחכן הוא. eloheichem gachchan hu.
Your God is like a funny kind of God דקאמר ליה ליחזקאל
שכב על צדך שמאלי וכתיב ושכבת על צדך הימני. de-ka-amar leih le-yechezkel
shechav al tzidecha semali u-chtiv ve-shachavta al tzidecha ha-yemani. He says to
יחזקאל Yechezkel something and then the opposite happens. He says to יחזקאל
Yechezkel lie on your left side but then it's written
lie on your right side. So what does he want, what does
he want from us? אתא ההוא תלמידא אמר ליה מאי טעמא דשביעתא?
ata hahu talmida amar leih mai taama de-shviata?
So now another person comes and says what is the reason for
שמיטה? shmita? אמר ליה השתא אמינא לכו מילתא דשויא לתרווייהו. amar leih
hashta amina lechu milta de-shavya le-tarveihu. I will give you an answer
that answers both of you, and what the answer will do is
connect the שמיטה shmita with יחזקאל, Yechezkel, but still leave more unclear
than clear. So just a heads up. Here is the answer. אמר
הקדוש ברוך הוא לישראל. amar ha-kadosh baruch hu le-yisrael. God said to
Israel. זרעו שש והשמיטו שבע. ziru shesh ve-hashmitu sheva.
You should sow for six years and do שמיטה shmita on the
seventh כדי שתדעו שהארץ שלי היא. kedei she-tedu she-ha-aretz sheli hi. You
should know that the land is Mine. והן לא עשו כן אלא
חטאו וגלו. ve-hen lo asu chen ela chatu ve-galu. They didn't do
it and they sinned and exiled. מנהגו של עולם מלך בשר ודם
שסרחה עליו מדינה אם אכזר הוא הורג את כולם. minhago shel olam
melech basar va-dam she-sarcha alav medina im achzar hu horeg et kulam.
The custom in the world is that if for a king that's
earthly, if a country, a province, whatever, is against him, then if
he's a cruel one he kills everybody. אם רחמן הוא הורג חציים.
im rachman hu horeg chetziyam. If he's merciful, he kills half of
them. אם רחמן מלא רחמים הוא מייסר הגדולים שבהם
בייסורין. im rachman malei rachamim hu meyaser ha-gdolim she-ba-hem be-yisurin. If he's
really like the chief merciful person possible, then he will only punish,
torment, however you want to translate, only the great one amongst them.
אף כך הקדוש ברוך הוא. af kach ha-kadosh baruch hu. This is
what הקדוש ברוך הוא ha-kadosh baruch hu did. All the Jewish people
right transgressed in the שמיטה shmita but מייסר את יחזקאל. meyaser et
yechezkel. Only יחזקאל Yechezkel was punished for that sin כדי למרק עוונותיהם
של ישראל, kedei le-marek avonoteihem shel yisrael, in order to cleanse the
transgressions of Israel. These questions about this 60 second question, is this
the suffering servant or even like Jesus in a sense dying for
your sins? What's the question though? Do they have, what are the
questions about this, about what this is saying theologically? Is that what,
do we believe that in other words יחזקאל Yechezkel was punished for
the sins of all the people? We say, I mean like we
started the page by saying it, that the father's sin and then
the sons have consequence at least if not punishment, consequence. Right, yeah,
but it's different. This is saying the... So the trope of having
a person who suffers, who carries the sins. Right, that's in our
tradition, that's, yeah, well, it's different than the Christians, so we say
that the suffering of the righteous can help atone for all of
us, but it's not a necessary atonement the way that traditional Christianity...
Right. It's also not a necessary path to God. Yeah. It's also
different because this isn't saying like, like I'm pretty sure in the
Christian tradition they would say Jesus wasn't like responsible for the sins
of the people, he was like completely clean and like the son
of God and just came in in order to take the sins
of the people, but this is saying יחזקאל Yechezkel was the like
גדול gadol among them, I would imagine, because he was the most
responsible for what was happening and he was the leader of the,
he was a leader in the diaspora as we saw him yesterday.
An innocent person being punished, he's like almost the most guilty person
being punished because... And sometimes these things happen nowadays, no? A leader
of the community or a leader of a bank or a leader
of a party will be more responsible than this...
sometimes.
But his punishment is moving from one side to the other? Yeah,
I don't get... Yeah, so like I don't know if that means
like if he's restless, he's, we saw him yesterday at the top
of ל"ח Lamed Chet יחזקאל Yechezkel as the leader of the... he,
we know him to be the leader of the גלות. Galut. So
is that connect to the שמיטה, Shmita, that because not keeping the
שמיטה Shmita there's exile, and יחזקאל Yechezkel as the leader of the
exile, you know, kind of pays for those sins or suffers or
works extra hard, so has that restlessness. But again, I think there's
like
lots more to say and explore than we have time and that
we can get into now. Okay, next one coming up. אמר ליה
ההוא מינא לרבי אבהו. Amar lei hahu mina l'Rabbi Abbahu. Next one,
okay? Challenges רבי אבהו. Rabbi Abbahu. אלהיכם כהן הוא. Eloheichem Kohen hu.
Your God is a priest, He's a כהן. Kohen. Why? How do
we learn it? He quotes a פסוק pasuk from שמות, Shemot, from
פרשת תרומה. Parashat Terumah. ויקחו לי תרומה. V'yikchu li trumah. Right? God
says to the Jewish people, 'Bring me תרומה.' trumah. If He gets
תרומה, trumah, therefore He's a כהן. Kohen. But problem,
כי קבריה למשה, ki kavrei l'Moshe, because this כהן Kohen also buried
משה, Moshe, right? במאי טביל? B'mai tavil? How,
what was his טבילה, tvila, right? What was his immersion between those
activities? וכי תימא במים? V'chi teima b'mayim? Is it possible that He
במים, b'mayim, is it possible that He dipped in water? והכתיב V'haktiv
from ישעיהו, Yeshayahu,
מי מדד בשעלו מים. Mi madad b'sha'alo mayim. So we're talking about
השם Hashem is so big that if He puts His foot in
the whole water of the earth, it's barely going to cover His
foot. So if He needs a מקווה, mikveh, where is He going
to go? אמר לו בנורא טביל. Amar lo b'nura tavil. רבי אבהו
Rabbi Abbahu says He dipped in fire. דכתיב כי הנה ה' באש
יבוא. D'chtiv ki hinei Hashem ba'esh yavo. He says because it says
השם Hashem comes through fire. ומי סלקא טבילותא בנורא? U'mi salka tviluta
b'nura? What, you're really serious?
Dipping in fire is valid, it's possible? There's baptism of fire. Baptism
of fire? בבקשה. Bevakasha. אמר לו אדרבה. Amar lo adraba. Yes, of
course. עיקר טבילותא בנורא. Ikar tviluta b'nura. The greater dipping, the greater
immersion is in fire. הוא דכתיב, Hu d'chtiv, and now we have
a פסוק pasuk from במדבר Bamidbar where the children of Israel are
taught how to purify the vessels that they got. וכל אשר לא
יבא באש
תעבירו במים. V'chol asher lo yavo ba'esh ta'aviru vamayim. I.e. anything that
cannot go through fire, put,
will go through water. I.e. the preferred method is through fire, but
if we can't, then do water.
Last one. So he didn't, so he didn't reject the idea that
God's a כהן. Kohen. Right. And a כהן Kohen that buried משה,
Moshe, right? But he explains how this might be possible. Okay. אמר
ליה ההוא מינא לרבי אבינא. Amar lei hahu mina l'Rabbi Abina. Last
one. כתיב מי כעמך ישראל גוי אחד בארץ. Ktiv mi k'amcha Yisrael
goy echad ba'aretz. מאי רבותייכו? Mai rabuteichu?
It says your nation of Israel are one, one nation in the
land. So how is this relationship between you and the nations? You're
one or you're like the גויים? goyim? מאי רבותייכו אתון נמי ערביתו
בהדן דכתיב כל הגוים כאין נגדו. Mai rabuteichu atun nami arvitu behadan
d'chtiv kol hagoyim k'ayin negdo.
On the one hand you're a גוי goy like the גויים, goyim,
you're a nation like everybody. On the other hand it says כל
הגוים כאין כנגדו, kol hagoyim k'ayin k'negdo, there's no one like you.
So which way is it? Like
is something very very very strong for me. Again that deserves tons
of time that what the powerful thing, most powerful thing about Judaism,
Jewish teachings, whatever we want to say, is that it's always a
this and that. If it was only one way, we'd lose it.
If it was only the other way, we'd lose it. But because
it is possible to have this and this. And that's something that's
hard to explain and hard to share. Okay, אמר ליה, מדידך הוא
אסהידו עלן, Mideidekh hu asaidu alan, like one of you already witnessed
that, already said. דכתיב, ובגוים לא יתחשב. Uvagoyim lo yitchashav.
So who said this? This is בלעם Bilam in his prophecy saying
you are alone among the nations.
How do we understand this? How do I understand this piece that
on one hand we have a uniqueness and on the other hand
we are like everybody else? רבי אלעזר רמי כתיב, Rabi Elazar rami
ktiv, he now we're gonna contrast a
פסוק pasuk and a parable. טוב ה' לכל Tov Hashem lakol וכתיב
טוב ה' לקוו. Uchtiv tov Hashem lekovav.
It says in two different places, one, השם Hashem is good to
everybody, and one, השם Hashem is good to לקוו. lekovav. קוה kaveh
is a very complicated שורש. shoresh. Any words that come to mind
from the שורש? shoresh? We just talked about it. Trust in him,
hope in him. So like לקוות lekavot hope, תקוה, tikvah, right, התקוה,
Hatikvah,
the hope, or מקוה. mikvah. So it's like a place of gathering,
like it's a where things come together. So השם Hashem on one
hand is good to everybody, on the other hand he's good to
those who hold on to him, who look up to him. משל,
Mashal, how do we understand it with a parable? לאדם שיש לו
פרדס, Leadam sheyesh lo pardes, like a person that has an orchard.
כשהוא משקה, Kshehu mashkeh, משקה את כולו. mashkeh et kulo. When he
waters, he waters the whole place. כשהוא עודר, Kshehu oder, אינו עודר
אלא טובים שבהם. eino oder ela tovim shebahem. When he hoes, when
he takes care of each tree individually, he doesn't just take care
automatically of all the trees, but only of the good ones, the
ones that will produce fruit. עודר Oder is like pruning?
I know it as hoe, H-O-E,
but if somebody has a different translation I'm open to hearing it.
They have hoes. What'd they say?
Alright, we're breathing, we're going back and picking up the next piece
of this משנה mishna before closing the פרק. perek. The last thing
in the משנה mishna if you want to just very briefly flip,
for me it's the last line in ל"ז ע"א, lamed zayin amud
aleph, לפיכך כל אחד ואחד חייב לומר בשבילי נברא העולם. Lefikach kol
echad ve’echad chayav lomar bishvili nivra ha’olam.
Therefore everyone has to say, for me the world was created. This
is again, if you recall, the witnesses and the value of each
person. So we're going to read just backtrack the משנה mishna because
it will help us understand. First of all the idea that חייב
לומר, chayav lomar, that we have to say it, it's not enough
to know this, we have to actually say it and remind ourselves
for our own sanity and for the value of others. בשבילי נברא
העולם. Bishvili nivra ha’olam. שמא תאמרו, Shema tomaru, now remember if you
remembered I'm in the משנה, mishna, מה לנו ולצרה הזאת, ma lanu
velatzara hazot, הלא כבר נאמר והוא עד או ראה או ידע אם
לא יגיד. halo kvar neemar vehu ed o ra’ah o yada im
lo yagid. So we can say, too much trouble to be a
witness, I don't want to do it, but it says no, you
should be a witness. ושמא תאמרו, veshema tomaru, מה
לנו לחוב בדמו של זה, ma lanu lachuv bedamo shel zeh, והלא
כבר נאמר באבוד רשעים רנה. vehalo kvar neemar ba'avod reshaim rinah.
So now the משנה mishna brings a פסוק pasuk, from משלי Mishlei
that says when the evildoers are lost, that brings joy. Okay, so
we need this for our גמרא Gemara on ל"ט ע"ב lamed tet
bet because the גמרא Gemara immediately jumps in and takes this word
רנה, rinah, joy, right? And will contrast two things. On one hand
we're supposed to be joyful when the evildoers pass from the world,
but that reminds the גמרא Gemara of another פסוק Pasuk and another
incident which is also a little complicated for our time, but we'll
try. ויעבר הרנה במחנה. Vaya'avor harinah bamachaneh.
If you look at the source, this is the story, I believe
the story of אחאב Achav who was king of Israel. At his
death, it says ויעבר הרנה במחנה, vaya'avor harinah bamachaneh,
like it was joyful in the camp. Yes sir.
While רנה rinah is clearly a song, Judaic Press sanitizes it and
translates it proclamation. כן, Ken,
it's like okay, I can live with it. The גמרא Gemara is
not so much concerned with that. The גמרא Gemara is concerned with
this little ה hey that this starts with, ויעבר הרנה, vaya'avor harinah,
because it can say ויעבר רנה, vaya'avor rinah, like
yeah it was joyful. What is that ה hey doing here? And
for our commentators, a ה hey is a red flag for or
a white and blue flag for reference to השם. Hashem. Okay. אמר
אביכא בר חנינא Amar Avicha bar Chanina takes, brings us back to
this פסוק, Pasuk. באבוד רשעים
רינה, Be'avod resha'im rina, when evildoers are lost, that is joyful.
Here is the example of אחאב. Achav. באבוד, Be'avod, or when we
lose אחאב בן עמרי רינה, Achav ben Omri rina, there was joy.
Also quick question on the text. If we're only talking about אחאב,
Achav, king of Israel, why רשעים resha'im in plural?
Some say that's his wife, איזבל, Izevel, that maybe the rest of
his family, because when he was lost, like when we're talking about
the witness, right, and קין Kayin and הבל Hevel and his blood,
the blood of his offspring,
calling from the earth, then that's also for אחאב. Achav.
But now we have a serious problem. ומי חדי קודשא בריך הוא
במפלתן של רשעים? U'mi chadei Kudsha Brich Hu bemapalatan shel resha'im?
Since when God is happy when the evildoers fall? Right? That's something
that's problematic. And what come immediately to the Song of the Sea
with the famous statement, הכתיב, Haktiv, it says, בצאת לפני החלוץ ואומרים
הודו להשם כי לעולם חסדו. Betzet lifnei hachalutz veomrim hodu Lashem ki
le'olam chasdo.
We have a quote from Chronicles that when the armies go out,
we say give thanks to להשם, Lashem, not for he is good,
but because he does kindness, he does like the right thing, but
we don't mention goodness.
And Rabbi Yochanan explains, מפני מה לא נאמר בהודאה זו כי טוב?
Mipnei mah lo ne'emar behoda'ah zu ki tov? Why does it not
say in this giving thanks כי טוב? ki tov? לפי שאין הקדוש
ברוך הוא שמח במפלתן של רשעים. Lefi she'ein Hakadosh Baruch Hu same'ach
bemapalatan shel resha'im. God is not happy with the downfall of the
evildoers. דאמר רב שמואל בר נחמני אמר רבי יוחנן, D'amar Rav Shmuel
bar Nachmani amar Rabbi Yochanan, מאי דכתיב? Mai dichtiv? Here's our famous
story. Remember what's written? Rav Shmuel says, what is it that's written
in שמות? Shmot? ולא קרב זה אל זה כל הלילה. Velo karav
zeh el zeh kol halaila. Right? We know that at the crossing
of the sea, the cloud and the fire stood and did not
come close to each other all night long. There's a lot, a
lot of commentaries around this. But the point being that there was
like a like a heavenly space between all the forces during that
night, and during that night, the מלאכים malachim came to השם. Hashem.
באותה שעה ביקשו מלאכי השרת לומר שירה לפני הקדוש ברוך הוא. Be'ota
sha'a bikshu mal'achei hasharet lomar shira lifnei Hakadosh Baruch Hu. During that
time, the מלאכי השרת mal'achei hasharet came in front of השם Hashem
to sing a song.
Again, lots of discussion around there. אמר להם הקדוש ברוך הוא, Amar
lahem Hakadosh Baruch Hu, מעשה ידי טובעים בים ואתם אומרים שירה לפני?
Ma'aseh yadai tove'im bayam ve'atem omrim shira lefanai? My creation is drowning
in the sea and you are saying a song?
But a little more fine-tuned, and also just to for the honesty
of the text, there's a lot of discussion which exactly שירה shira
is referred to here. Is it referring to the אז ישיר, Az
Yashir, which assuming everybody did sing, or is it referring to הלל?
Hallel? Are there situations where we say not a full הלל? Hallel?
What are those? Is that what the angels are doing here? So
I'm just referencing but bookmark then in our appetizers there's more to
eat in the kitchen. Okay. אמר רבי יוסי בר חנינא, Amar Rabbi
Yosi bar Chanina, הוא אינו שש אבל אחרים משיש. Hu eino sas,
aval acherim masis. דיקא נמי דכתיב Deika nami dichtiv ישיש Yasis ולא
כתיב ישוש. velo ktiv Yasus. שמע מינה. Shma mina.
Pause.
Rabbi Yosi bar Chanina teaches us a little Hebrew grammar that can
help us understand this a little better. It indeed says אינו שש.
eino sas. He himself is not happy. אבל אחרים משיש. Aval acherim
masis. This is the הפעיל. Hif'il. He causes others to be joyful.
And so it says in דברים, Devarim, right? Yes.
It says ישיש Yasis ולא כתב ישוש. velo ktav Yasus.
He's not himself happy, but he causes others to be happy when
the evildoers fall. You said opposite opinion in פרקי אבות Pirkei Avot
says don't rejoice when your enemy falls. Of course. Of course. That's
this is again that tension. You know, I mean like
to take the extreme example, when Hitler dies, what are we supposed
to do? Be sad? But the Jewish answer is always when you
ask a question, is it this or is it that? The answer
99% of the time is yes. There's a Yiddish saying, when your
enemy falls don't rejoice. Yes, alright.
Any of these situations, what are we supposed to do? Yes, the
answer is yes. All right. Since we're talking about אחאב, Achav, we're
going into another
whatever, it's like why, but but
we're talking about somebody who we consider in our history not good.
As a king he was
like negotiations and tried to establish the Kingdom of Israel. That's one
of the reasons he marries איזבל, Izevel, the Sidonite from Lebanon, right,
in order to create all these contracts, but he is bombarded with
attacks from ארם, Aram, like from Syria of today, and we know
his campaign against the prophets, השם's Hashem prophets, which comes to
heads between him and אליהו. Eliyahu. So this is the king of
Israel that is head-to-head with אליהו. Eliyahu.
Okay. We're bringing a פסוק Pasuk from the time of אחאב's Achav
death from Kings 1. והזונות רחצו. V'hazonot rachatzu.
Look at the פסוק. Pasuk וישטוף הרכב על ברכת שומרון וילוקו הכלבים
את דמו והזונות רחצו כדבר השם אשר דיבר. Vayishtof ha-rechev al birkat
shomron vayaloku haklavim et damo v'hazonot rachatzu kidvar Hashem asher diber. This
is the description of when אחאב Achav died.
His chariot was so full of blood, the dogs licked his blood
and זונות, Zonot, we'll see they have two opposite commentaries what that
is. The פשט Pshat is they're prostitutes, harlots, and they washed it
off so that he really had like a despised kind of death.
Okay, there was so much blood
and yes, that was the end. Okay. So now we're trying to
understand this פסוק pasuk in conjunction with אחאב, Achav, with how we
treat the evil doers. אמר רבי אליעזר, Amar Rabbi Eliezer, למרק שני
חזיונות של מיכה ושל אליהו. L'marek shnei hezyonot shel Micha v'shel Eliyahu.
Okay,
so רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer understands it not as זונות, Zonot, not
as prostitutes, but as
חזיונות, Hezyonot, visions, of two prophets. One is מיכה Micha and one
is אליהו. Eliyahu. במיכיהו כתיב, B'Michayahu ktiv, אם שוב תשוב בשלום לא
דיבר השם בי. Im shov tashuv b'shalom lo diber Hashem bi. If
you come back in peace, then this is not השם Hashem is
talking to not to me or to somebody else, unclear. באליהו כתיב,
B'Eliyahu ktiv, במקום אשר ליקקו הכלבים את דם נבות. Bimkom asher lik'ku
haklavim et dam Navot. Okay, so there's two prophecies about אחאב's Achav
death, where it's going to happen. אליהו Eliyahu says specifically it's the
place where the dogs licked נבות's Navot blood, which is another story
elsewhere with David, and מיכיהו Michayahu says it's going to be somewhere
else. Geographically, one talks about the גלעד, Gilad, which is, let's say,
southeast of כנרת, Kinneret, and one talks about the שומרון, Shomron,
and the center of אחאב's Achav kingdom is in the שומרון. Shomron.
Okay. So that's option one. Maybe והזונות רחצו, V'hazonot rachatzu, that they
wash, it's to clean up these two contradictory prophecies. And how? One
explanation is that he died in one place because he died like
by a stray arrow, which is what we know from Kings. He
died by a stray arrow, but then the chariot was led or
kept going to some place else, eventually leading his blood to the
שומרון. Shomron. So this is how both things possibly happened together. רבה
אמר, Rabba amar, on the other hand, he says זונות ממש. Zonot
mamash. No, we're talking about really prostitutes.
אחאב, Achav, in modern Hebrew מצונן Metsunan is that he has a
cold, but in the תלמוד Talmud he was frigid. Yes, he didn't
like sex,
he didn't like relationship, and asah lo איזבל, Izevel, wife, right,
she's a handful, so I don't think he had a lot of
room to move, and clearly a political marriage. She was a political
marriage but she's also like
powerful, anyway, ועשתה לו איזבל שתי צורי זונות במרכבתו. V'aseta lo Izevel
shtei tzurei zonot b'merkavto. She actually put those harlots in his chariot
כדי שיראה אותם ויתחמם. K'dei she-yireh otam v'yitchamem.
She wants him to warm up, hopefully to her, I guess, but
that's what they're sitting there for. Since we're talking about אחאב, Achav,
we're going to talk a little more about his death. Another peculiar
פסוק pasuk around his death, ואיש משך בקשת לתומו ויכה. V'ish mashach
b'keshet l'tumo vayakeh. This is how he died. Somebody pulled his bow
and arrow just like whatever, shooting into space and that arrow traveled
and hit
אחאב. Achav. Question is how do we understand this word לתמו? letumo?
רבי אלעזר אמר פשט לפי תומו, Rabbi Elazar amar peshat lefi tumo,
innocently, yes, that's just happened. אבל רבא אמר לתמם שתי חזיונות אחת
של מיכיהו ואחת של אליהו. But Rava amar letamem shtei chezyonot achat
shel michayahu ve'achat shel eliyahu. So we also know that the word
תם tam means complete, like יעקב איש תם, Yaakov ish tam, simple
in the sense that there's a oneness to it, there's a completion.
And רבא Rava says this is the meaning of that arrow, that
in his death both these prophecies are going to come together. All
right.
סימן קרב וזכה באדום, Siman krav vezakeh be'edom, so now the next
three quick
closing story statements. Since we're on אחאב, Achav, ויקרא אחאב אל עובדיהו
אשר על הבית ועובדיהו היה ירא השם מאוד. vayikra achav el ovadyahu
asher al habayit ve'ovadyahu haya yere hashem me'od. Another פסוק pasuk from
אחאב Achav is אחאב Achav called to עובדיה Ovadiah the prophet who
is in charge of his home
and עובדיה Ovadiah was very was fearing God very much. This word
will be important to us, this מאוד. me'od. מאי קאמר קרא, Mai
ka'amar kra, what
what is the text doing with this קרא? kra? Like what is
the relationship between the fact that אחאב Achav
calls עובדיה Ovadiah and the fact that עובדיה Ovadiah fears השם? Hashem?
It's like two stories that seemingly have nothing to do with each
other because said אחאב Achav called עובדיה Ovadiah and then he went
to do dishes. Like what does that have to do why do
we need to know that אחאב Achav calls עובדיה Ovadiah and that
עובדיה Ovadiah fears השם? Hashem? אמר רבי יצחק אמר לו, Amar rabbi
yitzchak amar lo,
so now really this is the subtext of what אחאב Achav says
to עובדיה Ovadiah behind the scenes. ביעקב כתיב נחשתי ויברכני השם בגללך.
Beyaakov ktiv nichashti vayivarchani hashem biglalecha.
In the story of יעקב, Yaakov, לבן Lavan says
השם Hashem blesses me, I know this, and השם Hashem blesses me
because of you. יעקב Yaakov I know that because you are with
me I am being blessed. I am not worthy, I am not
the righteous person here, but because of you השם Hashem blesses me.
ביוסף כתיב ויברך השם את בית המצרי בגלל יוסף. Veyosef ktiv vayivarech
hashem et beit hamitzri biglal yosef.
In יוסף Yosef it says השם Hashem blesses the house of the
Egyptian because of יוסף. Yosef. ביתיה דההוא גברא לא הוה מברך. Beiteih
dehai gufra lo hava mivarech.
My house, I'm not being blessed. So fine, I'm not perfect, but
you, you ירא השם מאוד. yere hashem me'od. So what's happening? I
find something very interesting that אחאב Achav tries to create the lineage
from יעקב Yaakov to יוסף Yosef to אחאב Achav because if you
recall the map of the tribes,
the kingdom of ישראל Yisrael is over אפרים Ephraim and מנשה, Menashe,
so he's trying to create his lineage that I should be like
יעקב, Yaakov, יוסף, Yosef, not דוד, David, right, not the house of
יהודה, Yehuda, and now me. Okay. שמא לא ירא אלוהים אתה. Shema
lo yere elohim ata. Maybe not really, maybe you're not really fearing
God. יצא בת קול ואמרה ועובדיהו היה ירא את השם מאוד. Yatza
bat kol ve'amra ve'ovadyahu haya yere et hashem me'od. עובדיה Ovadiah was
greatly fearing השם. Hashem. אבל ביתו של אחאב אינו מזומן לברכה. Aval
beito shel achav eino mezuman libracha.
Like like the bucket is not coming up basically. Even though he's
so fearing God, אחאב Achav is so far on the other side
that it is not it is not possible for him to even
is it? אמר רבא אמר רבא, Amar Rava amar Rava, גדול, gadol,
רגע רגע רגע, raga raga raga, גדול, gadol,
where are we? כן, ken, ה, ha,
the greatness is שנאמר בעובדיהו יותר ממה שנאמר באברהם דאילו באברהם לא
כתיב מאוד ובעובדיהו כתיב מאוד. shene'emar be'ovadyahu yoter mima shene'emar be'avraham de'ilu
be'avraham lo ktiv me'od uv'ovadyahu ktiv me'od. עובדיה Ovadiah even is more
fearing God than אברהם Avraham but yet not able to
overrule אחאב's Achav evil doing. Ah since we're talking about עובדיה, Ovadiah,
let's talk about עובדיה Ovadiah some more. אמר רבי יצחק מפני מה
זכה עובדיהו לנבואה? Amar rabbi yitzchak mipnei ma zacha ovadyahu linvu'ah? How
come עובדיה Ovadiah is a prophet? And we'll see what is the
problem. What is the problem with עובדיה Ovadiah being a prophet? Because
according to our tradition he's a convert. So
and there is a פסוק pasuk that says that God says I
will be to you to a God and to those after you.
I'm going to need like three more minutes to finish. Yes. Okay.
I'm going to be to a God to you and to your
offspring, to your seed afterwards, so there is an understanding that a
convert can't be a prophet because that lineage is not there and
עובדיה Ovadiah is a prophet, we'll see in a minute how is
this possible. So one explanation, מפני שהחבי מאה נביאים במערה. mipnei she'hechbi
me'ah nevi'im bame'arah.
During that campaign against the prophets he hides hundred prophets in a
cave, שנאמר. shene'emar, ויהי בהכרית איזבל את נביאי ה׳ ויקח עובדיהו מאה
נביאים ויחביאם חמישים איש במערה. vayehi behachrit izevel et nevi'ei Hashem vayikach
ovadyahu me'ah nevi'im vayachbi'em chamishim ish bame'arah. So, when איזבל, Izevel, אחאב's
Achav wife, does her campaign against Hashem prophets, Ovadyah takes 100 prophets
and hides them 50 in each cave. מאי שנא חמישים איש? mai
shena chamishim ish? What does it matter to her? What is the
point here that he hides 50? Why not 100? רבי אלעזר אמר
רבי אלעזר מיעקב למד. Rabbi Elazar amar Rabbi Elazar mi'Yaakov lamad.
Back again to that lineage. He learned from יעקב, Yaakov, שנאמר, and
funny coincidentally, I didn't see it anywhere but I'm just happy to
find connections so I'm sharing, this פסוק pasuk. is from וישלח Vayishlach
and so happens to be that the הפטורה haftorah for וישלח Vayishlach
is עובדיה. Ovadyah. סתם, stam, happens. Okay, והיה
המחנה הנשאר לפליטה. vehayah hamachaneh hanishar lifleitah.
So we know from יעקב Yaakov that when he comes to danger,
he splits the camp into two.
רבי אבהו אמר לפי שאין מערה מחזקת יותר מחמישים. Rabbi Abbahu amar
lefi she'ein me'arah machzeket yoter mechamishim. Simple. The מערה, me'arah, the cave,
cannot hold more than 50 people. So he had no choice, it
was nothing religious, spiritual, it was just practicality. You all get in
here, the others go cave B. Okay. Quote from the beginning of
the book of עובדיה Ovadyah which by the way is the shortest
book in the תנ״ך, Tanakh, one chapter. חזון עובדיהו כה אמר ה׳
אלוקים לאדום. chazon ovadyahu koh amar Hashem Elokim le'Edom.
Oh, if we're on עובדיה Ovadyah and we're talking about his lineage
and his prophecy and his relationship to the prophets, what is his
connection of דוקא davka having a vision, a prophecy for אדום? Edom?
מאי שנא עובדיה לאדום? mai shena ovadyah le'edom? What's the connection? אמר
רבי יצחק אמר הקדוש ברוך הוא יבוא עובדיה הדר בין שני רשעים
ולא למד ממעשיהם וינבא על עשו הרשע שדר בין שני צדיקים ולא
למד ממעשיהם. amar Rabbi Yitzchak amar Hakadosh Baruch Hu yavo ovadyah hadar
bein shenei resha'im velo lamad mima'aseihem veyinave al Esav harasha shedar bein
shenei tzadikkim velo lamad mima'aseihem. So the contrast between עובדיה Ovadyah and
עשו. Esav. עובדיה Ovadyah lived between two bad
guys, and the bad guys are איזבל Izevel and אחאב, Achav, that
he lives right in their house, he's the prophet of their palace,
and he still did not change his ways. And let him speak
to עשו Esav the evildoer who lived between righteous ones, right, יצחק
Yitzchak and רבקה, Rivka, and didn't learn from their doing. אמר אפרים
מקשאה תלמידו של רבי מאיר משום רבי מאיר דעובדיה גר אדומי היה.
amar Ephraim Maksha'ah talmido shel Rabbi Meir mishum Rabbi Meir de'ovadyah ger
edomi hayah. עובדיה Ovadyah really originally was an Edomite from an Edomite
family. והיינו דאמרי אינשי מיניה וביה אבא ניזיל ביה נרגא. vehainu de'amri
inshi mineih uveih abba nizil beih narga.
This is a also beautiful quick parable that says we're told that
the handle to the axe, axe,
comes from the forest. So that the destruction or the criticism it
comes from within. There's again tons to say about that but just
as a concept, sometimes it's awful, right, we have self-axes that beat
our own forest. Sometimes this is what happens. They bring us a
פסוק pasuk from King David: ויך את מואב וימדדם בחבל השכב אותם
ארצה. vayach et mo'av vayimadedem bechevel hashkev otam artzah.
King David also warred,
had a war against מואב. Mo'av. And what do we know about
King David's
lineage? That he's from מואב. Mo'av. Right, so we've seen it before,
looks similar. אמר רבי יוחנן משום רבי שמעון בר יוחאי היינו דאמרי
אינשי מיניה וביה אבא ניזל ביה נרגא. amar Rabbi Yochanan mishum Rabbi
Shimon bar Yochai hainu de'amri inshi mineih uveih abba nizal beih narga.
This repeats the same sentence we just read a line earlier. אבא
abba here in the meaning of a forest, נרגא, narga, the גרזן,
garzen, the axe. So the handle of the axe comes from the
forest. And this could go the other way too. Which other way?
Apostate Jews have caused us a lot of damage. Yes, yes. So
this is what I'm saying like it can be, yes, because like
know your enemy or from inside already you have the tools. And
also as an individual, like you know sometimes from within we can
create more criticism than out. And רב דימי Rav Dimi brings another
example, ירך מתוכה מסרחת, yerech mitochah masrachat, גסאי gasa'ei is like it
stinks from within itself. Okay,
another פסוק. Sorry. ויקח את בנו הבכור אשר ימלוך תחתיו ויעלהו לעולה
על החומה. vayikach et beno habechor asher yimloch tachtav vaya'alehu le'olah al
hachomah.
This is another incident
later on in מלכים Melachim of a leader who takes his older
son that supposedly king under him and sacrifices him on the wall.
רב ושמואל חד אמר לשם שמים וחד אמר לשם עבודה זרה. Rav
u'Shmuel chad amar leshem shamayim vechad amar leshem avodah zarah. Why did
they do this? One for the sake of heaven and one said
for the sake of heaven, one for עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. בשלמא
למאן דאמר לשם שמים היינו דכתיב ויהי קצף גדול על ישראל. bishlama
leman de'amar leshem shamayim hainu dechtiv vayehi ketzef gadol al yisrael.
So, both of them bring
a פסוק to prove their point, that it could have been for
the sake of heaven, it could have been. How do you explain
that anger? כדהרבי יהושע בן לוי, Kede'rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, דהמרבי יהושע
בן לוי רמי, de'amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi rami, כתיב
וכמשפטי הגויים אשר סביבותיכם לא עשיתם. Kativ u'chemishpetei ha'goyim asher svivoteichem lo
asitem.
You should not, you shouldn't do or you haven't done like the
judgments of the גויים goyim around you. וכתיב כי כמשפטי הגויים אשר
סביבותיכם עשיתם. U'chtiv ki chemishpetei ha'goyim asher svivoteichem asitem. Yes, so again
another tension, another contradiction. Did you not do like the judgments of
the גויים goyim of the nations around you or did you, huh?
Customs. Okay, like the customs or did you? Which way did you
go? And they answer, the גמרא Gemara gives, כמתוקנים שבהם לא עשיתם
כמקולקלים שבהם עשיתם. kamtukanim shebahem lo asitem kemkulkalim shebahem asitem.
The good ones you didn't learn, the bad ones you did learn.
ויסעו מעליו וישבו לארץ. Vayisu mealav vayashuvu la'aretz. אמר רבי חנינא בר
פפא, Amar Rabbi Chanina bar Papa, באותה שעה, be'otah sha'ah, at that
time, ירדו רשעים של ישראל למדרגה
תחתונה. yardu resha'im shel Yisrael l'madrega tachtona. The evildoers of Israel went
down all the way to the lowest level as it is said,
והנערה יפה עד מאוד. vehanara yafah ad me'od. They reached עד ad
until very deeply. אמר רבי חנינא בר פפא, Amar Rabbi Chanina bar
Papa, עדיין לא הגיע לחצי יפיה של שרה, adayin lo higiya l'chatzi
yafyah shel Sarah, דכתיב עד מאוד ולא מאוד בכלל. de'chtiv ad me'od
v'lo me'od bichlal. They only reached until very much, but didn't make
it all. Maybe that would be a merit. הדרן עלך אחד דיני
ממונות. Hadran alach echad dinei mamonot. Thank you for completing fourth chapter
in סנהדרין Sanhedrin with us this morning. More to come. All right.
We need to do something with this. Thank you. There is a
very רגע רגע רגע. rega rega rega. There is a very serious
problem with the incident of the king of מואב. Moav. Kill each
other. Okay. And this.